ANIL KUMAR

Profile

A molecular biologist with more than 15 years of research experience in academia & industry, now excited about transitioning into the field of information technology/computational biology by acquiring Python and Java skills. Has worked on wide range of projects involving genetic engineering of plants, microalgae, fungi, yeast and bacteria aimed at increasing crop yields, biofuel production, control of plant pathogenic fungi, dsRNA & protein production.

Contact Details

+1614-804-3787



anilkumar21k@gmail.com



1282 White Road Chesterfield, MO 63017

Education

PhD in Plant Cellular and Molecular Biology from Ohio State University, Columbus, OHIO, USA

Masters in Genetics and Plant Breeding from University of Agricultural Sciences, Bangalore, INDIA

Programming Skills

Python, Java, Springboot, Thymeleaf, HTML, CSS, SQL.

Project Experience

Developed a restaurant finding tool that allows users to find restaurants based on city or zip code. The application provides users with a list of restaurants with restaurant address and their location on Google maps. The restaurant list contains links to restaurant menu. The application

also provides options for users to make reservations for dining or placing orders for delivery or pickup.

Statistical Skills

Experience with use of experimental designs, probability, one way and two-way ANOVA for analysis of experimental data. Have also been exposed to basics of NumPy and Matplotlib.

Work Experience

2015 – Present: Senior Scientist at RNAgri/APSE Inc.

Currently working at a biotech startup working towards development of technology for large scale production of dsRNA for applications in Agriculture and for Urban & Structural pest control.

2014-2015: Senior Scientist at K. Life Sciences

Lead research efforts at KLS, an early stage start up that worked towards development of RNAi based strategies to control plant fungal pathogens.

2011 -2014: Senior Scientist at Logos Energy

Lead research efforts at Logos Energy, a biofuel company involving genetic engineering of microalgae to enhance lipid production in microalgae and to develop other novel applications of engineered microalgae.

Awards/Grants

2017: United States Department of Agriculture (USDA) Phase1 Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) grant of \$100K for "Development of RNA interference-based product for Red Imported Fire Ant (*Solenopsis invicta* Buren) control".

2012: USDA Phase I SBIR grant of \$100K for development of "RNA interference-based oral therapeutant for White Spot Syndrome Virus of shrimp".

2006: Recipient of "award for best Oral presentation" at Plant Molecular Biology and Biotechnology symposium at Wooster, Ohio.